<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The capitulations and articles of peace between the Majesty of the King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. and the Sultan of the Ottoman Empire as they have been augmented and altered in the times of several ambassadors, and particularly as they have been renewed, augmented, and amplified at the city of Adrianople in the month of January 1661/2, by Heneage, Earl of Winchelsea, Ambassador Extraordinary from His Majesty : and also as they have been since renewed in the month of September 1675 : with divers additional articles and priviledges, by Sir John Finch, to Sultan Mahomet Han, the most puissant Prince and Emperour of the Turks.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc. Turkey, 1662 Jan.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12937327</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12937327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95808</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95808)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 733:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The capitulations and articles of peace between the Majesty of the King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. and the Sultan of the Ottoman Empire as they have been augmented and altered in the times of several ambassadors, and particularly as they have been renewed, augmented, and amplified at the city of Adrianople in the month of January 1661/2, by Heneage, Earl of Winchelsea, Ambassador Extraordinary from His Majesty : and also as they have been since renewed in the month of September 1675 : with divers additional articles and priviledges, by Sir John Finch, to Sultan Mahomet Han, the most puissant Prince and Emperour of the Turks.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc. Turkey, 1662 Jan.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>Mehmed IV, Sultan of the Turks, 1642-1693.</author>
                  <author>Turkey. Treaties, etc. England and Wales, 1662 Jan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 5-45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Turkey --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:95808:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 
                  <date>April 13. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>LET the following Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made with the <hi>Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> be Printed for the uſe of the <hi>Turkey</hi>-Company.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jo. Cooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95808:1"/>
            <p>THE Capitulations AND ARTICLES OF PEACE BETWEEN The Majeſty of the King of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> AND The SULTAN of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, As they have been augmented and altered in the times of ſeveral Ambaſſadors:</p>
            <p>And particularly as they have been renewed, augmented, and amplified at the City of <hi>Adrianople</hi> in the Month of <hi>January</hi> 1661/2. by <hi>Heneage</hi> Earl of <hi>Winchelſea,</hi> Ambaſſador Extraordinary from his Majeſty: And alſo as they have been ſince renewed in the Month of <hi>September</hi> 1675. with divers additional Articles and Priviledges, by Sir <hi>John Finch,</hi> Knight, Ambaſſador in Ordinary from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to <hi>Sultan Mahomet Han,</hi> the moſt puiſſant Prince and Emperour of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. S.</hi> MDCLXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95808:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95808:2"/>
            <head>The Articles of Peace, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">ACcording to my Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand let it be obſerved, and let no Act be permitted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereunto.</head>
            <head>MAHOMET.</head>
            <p>THE Command of this Sublime, and Loſty, and Imperial Signature, preſerved and exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Divine Providence, whoſe Triumph and Glory is renowned through all the World.</p>
            <p>By the favour of the Nouriſher of all things, and mercy and grace of the merciful, I that am the powerful Lord of Lords of the World, whoſe Name is formidable upon Earth, giver of all Crowns of the Univerſe, <hi>Sultan Mahomet Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Ibrahim Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Ahmet Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Mahomet Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Murat Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Selim Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Suliman Han,</hi> Son of <hi>Sultan Selim Han.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the glorious amongſt the great Princes of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> reverenced by the high Potentates of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95808:3"/>of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſole Director of the important Affairs of the <hi>Nazarene</hi> Nation, Lord of the limits of Decency, and honour of Greatneſs, and Fame, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> that is of <hi>Great Brittain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> whoſe end and Enterpriſes may the Omnipotent God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with bliſs and favour, with the illumination of his holy will.</p>
            <p>In times paſt the Queen of the aforeſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſent divers of her eſteemed Gentlemen, and Perſons of Quality, with Letters and Ships to this Imperial High Port (the refuge of the Princes of the World, and the retreat of the Kings of the whole Univerſe) in the happy times of famous memory of my Anceſtors now placed in Paradiſe, whoſe Souls be repleniſhed with Divine Mercy; which Gentlemen and Preſents were gratefully accepted, making Declaration, and offering, in the Name of the ſaid Queen, an entire good Peace, and pure Friendſhip, and demanding that their Subjects might have leave to come from <hi>England</hi> into our Ports. Our ſaid Anceſtors of happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory did then grant their Imperial Licenſe, and gave into the hands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation divers eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial and Imperial Commands, to the end that they might ſafely and ſecurely come and go into theſe Dominions, and in coming or returning either by Land or Sea in their way and paſſage, that they ſhould of no man be moleſted or hindered. After which time in the days of our Grandfather <hi>Sultan Mahomet Han</hi> of famous memory (unto whoſe Soul be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divine Abſolution) it being a-new deſired, That the Subjects, Merchants, and their Interpreters, might freely and ſecurely come, Merchandize, and Negotiate through all the parts of this Imperial
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95808:3"/>Dominion, and that ſuch Capitulations, and other Priviledges, and Imperial Commands, as had been granted unto the Nation of the Kings and Princes in Peace and Amity with this high Port, as <hi>France, Venice, Poland,</hi> and others, might alſo be granted to the Subjects of the ſaid Queen, and all others coming under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Banner; in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of which requeſt, were given and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by our Anceſtors of famous memory, the Imperial Capitulations and Priviledges ſucceeding, to ſay, It is commanded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Our Ships may trade in all parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>I. Firſt, That the ſaid Nation, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and any other Nation or Merchants which are or ſhall come under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Banner and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, with their Ships ſmall and great, Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, Faculties, and all other their Goods, may always paſs ſafe in our Seas, and freely and in all ſecurity may come and go into any part of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial limits of our Dominions in ſuch ſort, that neither any of the Nation, their Goods and Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall receive any hindrance or moleſtation from any perſon whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Travel freely.</note>II. The ſaid Nation ſhall and may in like manner freely and ſecurely come and go by Land through all the Imperial Limits of our Dominions, ſo that neither to their Perſons, Beaſts, Goods, or Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhall any trouble or Impediment be given, nor any injury be done unto them, but they ſhall always at their own pleaſures ſafely and ſecurely traffick in all parts of our Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſame.</note>III. And if it happen that any of the ſaid Nation coming into our Dominions by Land, or paſſing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95808:4"/>into any other Country ſhall be ſtayed or arreſted by any of our Miniſters, ſuch perſons ſhall be ſet free and at liberty, and afterwards ſhall receive no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance in his Journey.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. All <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships or Veſſels, ſmall or great, ſhall and may at any time ſafely and ſecurely come and harbour in any of the Scales and Ports of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and likewiſe may from thence depart at their pleaſure, without detention or hindrance of any man.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Diſtreſs of Ships</note>V. And if it ſhall happen that any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel, great or ſmall, fall into any misfortune, danger of Sea, or any other neceſſity, all the Veſſels, as well Imperial, as belonging to private men, that ſhall be near or preſent, as alſo all others that inhabit the Seas, ſhall give them help and ſuccour; and being come into our Ports or Scales, they ſhall freely ſtay in them as long as they pleaſe, and for their money provide for them of all neceſſaries, and Proviſion,<note place="margin">Freedom to take Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> and may take Water without the let or hindrance of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. And if it ſhall happen that any of their Ships ſhall have ſuffered Shipwrack,<note place="margin">Caſes of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack.</note> or been broken, or in diſtreſs, ſhall be caſt upon any Coaſt of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; in which caſe all Beglarbegs, Cadees, Governours, Miniſters, and other our Slaves, ſhall give them all aſſiſtance, ſuccour and help; and whatſoever Goods, and Faculties ſhall be ſaved or recovered in the ſaid Ships, ſhall be reſtored to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and if they ſhall be reſtored to the of their Goods and Faculties ſhall be ſtole or taken away, our ſaid Miniſters, with all diligence, ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95808:4"/>make ſufficient ſearch and examination to find out and recover the Goods, and reſtore them to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants to travel freely.</note>VII. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, Interpreters, Brokers, and all other Subjects of that Nation, whether by Sea or Land, may freely and ſafely come and go in all the Ports of our Dominions, or returning into their own Country, all our Beglerbegs, Miniſters, Governours, and other Officers, Captains by Sea of Ships, and others whomſoever our Slaves and Subjects, we command that none of them do or ſhall lay hands upon their perſons, or Faculties, or upon any pretence ſhall do them any hinderance or injury.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">One <hi>Engliſh</hi> man not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for the Debt of another, unleſs he be his Surety by Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</note>VIII. If any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, either for his own Debt, or for Surety-ſhip, ſhall abſent himſelf, or make eſcape away, or ſhall be bankerupt, the Creditor ſhall only pretend his Debt upon his own Debtor, and not of any other <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and if the Creditor have not authentick Hoget or Bill of Surety-ſhip made by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, he ſhall not pretend his Debt of any other <hi>Engliſh</hi> man.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. In all Cauſes, Buſineſſes and Occaſions which ſhall occur between the ſaid Nation, their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Interpreters and Brokers, or Servants, and any other whatſoever, that is to ſay, In felling or buying, in paying or receiving, in giving or taking ſecurity, or Pledge, Debt or Credit, and all other ſuch things which appertain to the Miniſters of the Law and Juſtice,<note place="margin">In all buſineſſes nothing of force without Hoget.</note> they may always (if they pleaſe) in ſuch occaſions go to the Caddee, who is the Judge of the Law, and there make a Hoget, or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95808:5"/>publick Authentick Act with Witneſs, and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame, and take a Copy of the ſame to keep by them, to the end that if in the future any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or pretence ſhall ariſe between the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they may both have a recourſe to the ſaid Hoget and Act. And when the pretence ſhall be conformable to the tenor of the Hoget Regiſtred; then it ſhall be accordingly thereunto obſerved: And if the Plaintiff hath not in his hands any ſuch Authentick Hoget, but only bringeth partial Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which makes Cavils or Pretences, our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall not give ear to them, but obſerve the written authentick Hoget.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <note place="margin">No plea to be made againſt an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man without knowledge of the Embaſſad. Or Conſul</note>X. And if any one within our Dominions ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man to have done him wrong, and ſhall therefore raiſe any pretence upon him by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent or partial Witneſs, our Miniſters ſhall not give car unto them, nor accept them, but the Cauſe ſhall be adviſed to the Embaſſadour or Conſul Reſident of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, to the end that the buſineſs may be decided with his knowledge, and in his preſence, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> may always have recourſe to their defence and protection.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. If any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, having committed an offence, ſhall make his eſcape,<note place="margin">No <hi>Engliſh</hi> man to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without being pledge.</note> or abſent himſelf, no other <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, not being pledge, ſhall be taken or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted for him.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> men not to be Slaves.</note>XII. All <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, or Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> which be found Slaves in our ſtate, or ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Embaſſadour, or Conſul, the cauſe ſhall be duly examined, and ſuch perſons as are found truly to be Subjects of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95808:5"/>ſet free, and delivered to the Embaſſadour, or Conſul.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <note place="margin">No <hi>Harach</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</note>XIII. All Engliſh-men, and all other Subjects of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> which ſhall dwell, or reſide in our Dominions, whether they be married, or ſingle; may buy, ſell, and traffick, and of them ſhall no <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi> or Head-money be demanded.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <note place="margin">The Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour<hi>'s</hi> power to conſtitute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls.</note>XIV. The Engliſh Embaſſadour, Reſident in <hi>Aleppo, Alexandria, Tripoli</hi> of <hi>Suria,</hi> or <hi>Tunis; Algier, Tripoli</hi> of <hi>Barbary,</hi> in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> the Ports of <hi>Cairo,</hi> or any other parts of our Dominions, may at their pleaſure eſtabliſh their Conſuls, and in like manner remove them, or change and appoint others in their places, and none of our Miniſters ſhall oppoſe, or refuſe to accept them.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <note place="margin">No Proceſs without the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter.</note>XV. In all Cauſes concerning Law and Juſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and any other, in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their Interpreters, the Judges, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther of our Miniſters, ſhall not proceed to give Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Turks</hi> not to meddle in differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </note>XVI. If there happen any Controverſie amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the deciſion thereof ſhall be wholly left to their own Embaſſadour or Conſul, according to their own Right and Laws, and with no ſuch Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes our Miniſters ſhall intermeddle.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <note place="margin">Our Ships not to be detained at Sea by the <hi>Turks</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mada.</note>XVII. Our Armada of Gallies, Ships, or any other Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of our Empire, which at Sea meet, or find any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship, they ſhall not do them, nor ſuffer to be done to them the leaſt injury, or trouble; nor ſhall they ſtay them, demand, pretend, or take any thing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95808:6"/>from them, but ſhall ſalute, and ſhew good and mutual Friendſhip the one to the other, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <note place="margin">All Priviledges granted to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, granted alſo to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </note>XVIII. All thoſe particular Priviledges and Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which in former times have been granted to the <hi>French, Venetians,</hi> or any other Chriſtian Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe King is in Peace and Friendſhip with this Port, in like manner, the ſame were granted, and given to the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; to the end, that in time to come, the Tenour of this our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Capitulations may be always obſerved by all men; and that none may, in any manner, upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretence, preſume to contradict, or violate it.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. If the Pyrates, or <hi>Levents,</hi> who infeſt the Seas with their Frigates,<note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Pyrates.</note> ſhall be found to have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel, or to have robbed or ſpoiled their Goods and Faculties: Alſo if it ſhall be found, that in any of our Dominions, any ſhall have violently taken Goods of any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, our Miniſters ſhall with all diligence ſeek out ſuch Offenders, and ſeverely puniſh them, and cauſe that all ſuch Goods, Ships, Moneys, and whatſoever hath been taken away from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, juſtly, and abſolutely reſtored to them.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. All our <hi>Beglerbegs, Begs,</hi> Captains, Maſters of Imperial Ships, and other private Judges, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Cuſtomers, Farmers, and all our Miniſters, Subjects and Slaves, ſhall always obey and keep the Tenour of theſe our Sworn Capitulations, and ſhall with all obſervance reſpect the Friendſhip and good Correſpondence eſtablished on both Parties, every one in particular taking eſpecial care not to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95808:6"/>commit any Act contrary thereunto. And as long as the ſaid Queen of <hi>England,</hi> according to this preſent Agreement of ſincere Friendſhip, and good Correſpondence, ſhall ſhow her ſelf, and remain with us in Peace, Friendſhip, and League, firm, conſtant, and ſincere; We do promiſe alſo on our parts reciprocally, that this Peace, Friendſhip, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, Capitulations, and Correſpondence in the fore-written form, ſhall be for ever of us maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, obſerved, and reſpected; and of no man many part thereof ſhall be contradicted, or infringed: All which above-mentioned Articles of Peace and Friendſhip were concluded ſigned, and an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Capitulation granted and confirmed by our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors of happy Memory.</p>
            <p>Since which time his Majeſty of <hi>England, James</hi> deceaſed in the time of our Grand-Father of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py memory, Sultan <hi>Achmet Han,</hi> having ſent unto our Imperial Throne his Embaſſadours, Letters, and Preſents, which were moſt acceptable, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that the already contracted Peace, and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and good Correſpondence made with our Grand-fathers, and the Capitulations, Articles, and Priviledges above-written, ſhould be again ratified, and the ſaid Peace and Frendſhip renewed; far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requeſting, that certain Articles very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould to the ſame Capitulations be added. The deſire of his Majeſty, being declared in the Imperial Preſence of our ſaid Grand-Father Sultan <hi>Achmet Han,</hi> was preſently granted: And he gave expreſs Command and Order, that the ſaid Peace and Friendſhip ſhould be renewed and fortified, and the Ancient Capitulations and Priviledges confirmed; and that the new deſired Articles ſhould be inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and added to the Imperial Capitulations:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95808:7"/>Granting farther to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, all thoſe Articles and farther Priviledges which were, given, and written in any Capitulations with other, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Potentates, or Kings in Peace and Amity with this Imperial Port: And by this Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand he gave order, that theſe his Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſhould be obeyed of all men, and the Tenour of them duly obſerved. The Articles which then were granted, and added to the Capitulations, were theſe following.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. That our Miniſters ſhall not demand, or take of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation any Cuſtom,<note place="margin">No Cuſtom to be taken on Moneys. None to force change of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys.</note> or other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of all the Dollars and Chequeens, they, or an under their Banner ſhall bring in, or tranſport from place to place, or carry out of our Dominions; and that neither Beglerbegs, Begs, Caddees, Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Mint-Maſters, or other, ſhall take and demand either Dollars or Chequeens from the ſaid Nation, to change them into ſmall Aſpers; nor ſhall give or do them any violence or trouble thereupon.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and all thoſe that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Banner, their Veſſels, ſmall and great, ſhall and may navigate, traffick, buy, ſell, and abide in all parts of our Dominions;<note place="margin">No Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in our Ships.</note> and excepting Arms, Gun-powder, and other ſuch prohibited Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, they may load, and carry away in their Ships, whatſoever of our Merchandizes, at their own pleaſure, without the impeachment or trouble of any man; and their Ships and Veſſels may come ſafely and ſecurely to Anchor at all times,<note place="margin">Proviſions may be bought for our Ships.</note> and traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick at all times in every part of out Dominions, and with their Money buy Victuals, and all other things, without any contradiction, or hinderance of any man.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95808:7"/>
               <note place="margin">No Proceſs to be made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſence of the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>XXIII. And if any difference ſhall happen with any of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, by Suit in Law, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Controverſie, the Caddees, or any other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of our Juſtice, ſhall not hear nor decide the Cauſe, until the Embaſſadour, Conſul, or Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger-man of the ſaid Nation ſhall be preſent.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <note place="margin">Suit of Law above <hi>4000 Aſpers</hi> to be heard above.</note>XXIV. All differences, or Suits of Law depending with the ſaid Nation, which ſhall exceed the value 4000 Aſpers, ſhall always be heard and decided at our Imperial Port.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <note place="margin">No Conſul to be impriſoned, nor diſmiſſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>XXV. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nations Conſul, or Reſident in any Port of our Dominions, being eſtabliſhed by the Embaſſadour, Reſident for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, our Miniſters ſhall have no power to impriſon, or exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or ſeal up their Houſes, nor to diſmiſs or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place them from their Charge and Office; but in caſe of any difference, or Suit with the Conſul, there ſhall he made a Certificate to the Imperial Port, to the end that the Embaſladour may protect and anſwer for them.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <note place="margin">The Goods of <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men dying, not to Eſchent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>XXVI. When any Engliſh-man, or other under their Banner ſhall die in our Dominions, with their Goods or Faculties, or any thing that belonged unto them, our Eſcheators, Caddees, or other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, upon pretence they are Goods of the Dead, without any Owner, ſhall not meddle, take, or ſeize any part thereof, but they ſhall always be conſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and remaining to ſuch other <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd ſhall by his Teſtament aſſign; and if he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inteſtate, then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſul ſhall take and receive his, Faculties and Goods; and if there be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95808:8"/>no Conſul, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reſident there ſhall take the Poſſeſſion; and in caſe there be neither Conſul, nor <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the ſaid Goods and Faculties whatſoever, ſhall be received into the cuſtody of the Caddee of that place; and having adviſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour thereof, the ſaid Caddee ſhall reſign all the ſaid Goods unto ſuch Perſons as the Embaſſadour ſhall ſend with Commiſſion to receive them.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. All theſe Priviledges, and other Liberties granted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and thoſe who come under their Protection, by divers Imperial Commands, whether before or after the date of theſe Imperial Capitulations, ſhall be always obeyed and obſerved, and ſhall always be underſtood and interpreted in favour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, according to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and true Contents thereof.</p>
            <p n="28">
               <note place="margin">In eaſes of Death, the <hi>Cadee</hi> not to meddle.</note>XXVIII. Neither the Officer, called the <hi>Caſſam,</hi> or Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of the Caddees Duties, in caſe of death, nor the Caddee, ſhall pretend or take of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, any kind of Tenths, or Gaſmets, or Fee of Diviſion.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <note place="margin">No <hi>Janizary, &amp;c.</hi> to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on us without our conſent.</note>XXIX. The Embaſſadour of the King of <hi>England,</hi> or Conſul reſiding in our Dominion, ſhall and may take into their ſervice any <hi>Janizary,</hi> or Interpreter, at their own charge and choice; and no <hi>Janizary,</hi> nor other our Slaves, ſhall put themſelves, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with their ſervice againſt their liking or conſent.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. The Embaſſadour of his Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> and Conſul, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation-reſiding in our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, for the uſe of their own Perſons and Families,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95808:8"/>making Muſt or Wine in their own Houſes, none of our Miniſters, Caddees, or <hi>Janizaries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For making Wine.</note> ſhall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt or hinder them, or demand any Duties or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or do them any violence or impediment.</p>
            <p n="31">
               <note place="margin">Cuſtoms paid in one Port, are not to be demanded in another.</note>XXXI. In the Port of <hi>Conſtantinople, Aleppo, Alexandria, Scio, Smyrna,</hi> and in other parts of our Dominions, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants having paid the Cuſtom of their Merchandize, according to the Tenour of the Imperial Capitulations, no man ſhall moleſt, or trouble, or take from them any thing more; and whatſoever Merchandize ſhall be loaden upon their Ships, and brought in our Dominions, and landed at any Scale, they being deſirous to lade it again, and to tranſport it to any other Scale, or Port, the ſame Goods arriving in the ſecond place, and Scale, and being there unladen, neither the Cuſtomer, nor Farmers, nor any other our Officers, ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or take again any Cuſtoms, or Gabels of the ſaid Merchandize; that the ſaid Nation may always freely and ſecurely trade, and follow their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="32">
               <note place="margin">No <hi>Haſſapie</hi> Duties.</note>XXXII. Neither of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, nor of any tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding under their Banner, there ſhall not be demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor gathered one Aſper, nor any Money in the name of Impoſition <hi>Haſſapie,</hi> or Compoſitions for Fleſh for the <hi>Janizaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. There having been in times paſt a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Embaſſadour of the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour, both reſident in our Port, about the Merchants of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Nation; both which Embaſſadours ſent their Petitions to our Imperial Stirrup, and made requeſt, that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95808:9"/>ſaid <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants, coming into our Dominions, ſhould paſs under their Banner; which Requeſt of both Embaſſadours was granted under our Imperial Seal; notwithſtanding <hi>Sinan Baſſa,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gala,</hi> Captain of the Sea, now deceaſed, as Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and practiſed in Maritime caſes, having adviſed the Imperial Majeſty, that it was fit and convenient that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Nation ſhould be aſſigned to the Protection of the Embaſſadour of <hi>England,</hi> and that it ſhould be ſo written in their Capitulations: which Opinion being by all the Viziers approved, by Expreſs Order, and Imperial Authority it was commanded, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Holland, Zealand, Freezeland,</hi> and <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derland;</hi> that is, the Merchants of thoſe four Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, trading in our Dominions, ſhall always come under the Banner of the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> as all other <hi>Engliſh</hi> do; and that of all the Goods and Merchandize which they ſhall or do import or export,<note place="margin">All Straugers to come under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Protection.</note> to and from our Dominions in their Veſſels, they ſhall pay the Duties of Conſulage, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties, to the Embaſſadour or Conſul of the Queen of <hi>England;</hi> and that never hereafter the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour or Conſul ſhall inſinuate nor intermeddle herein: And accordingly it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that for the time to come it ſhould be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and obſerved, according to this preſent Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation.</p>
            <p>After which, there being arrived an other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour at this High Port, ſent from the King of <hi>England,</hi> with Letters and Preſents, which were moſt acceptable, the ſaid Embaſſadour did make requeſt, that certain other neceſſary Articles ſhould be added, and written in the Imperial Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95808:9"/>of which the firſt was, As in times paſt, in the days of one of our Fore-fathers of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, Sultan <hi>Soliman Han,</hi> there was granted a certain Capitulation and Priviledge, that the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation, <hi>Portugal, Ancona, Sevilla, Florence, Catalonia,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and other Merchant-Strangers, might ſafely and ſecurely go, and come through all the places of our Dominions, and trade and traffick; granting unto them, moreover, that in any part of our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire they might eſtabliſh their Conſuls: But it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that every Nation apart was not able to defray the Charges and Maintenance of a Conſul, it was then left to their will and choice, to come under the Banner of ſuch Embaſſadour or Conſul as ſhould beſt like them, provided that it were an Embaſſadour or Conſul of a King in Peace and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with our High Port; upon which Grant, and other Priviledges given them, there were often granted divers Imperial Commands and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, being ſo deſired by Merchant-Strangers, who of their own will elected to trade under the Banner and Protection of the Embaſſadour and Conſul of the King of <hi>England.</hi> And whileſt in all Scales and Ports in theſe parts, they had refuge to the Banner and Protection of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſuls: It ſeemeth, that the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour by ſome means having a new gotten into their Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that the ſaid Merchant-Strangers ſhould come under their Banner, did endeavour to force them in all Scales to their Protection; for which cauſe the Controverſie was again renewed and referred to our <hi>Divan,</hi> or Great Council, which after a due Examination, and a new Election, permitted to the will and choice of the ſaid Merchants, they again
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95808:10"/>did deſire to be under the Protection of the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour of the King of <hi>England,</hi> notwithſtanding it being made known to the Imperial Port, that as yet the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour did not deſire to moleſt the ſaid Merchants, nor to force them under his Protection, the firſt Article written in the <hi>French</hi> Capitulations, that the Merchants-Strangers ſhould come under their Protection, was by the Imperial Command made void and annulled: And to the end, that according to the ancient Cuſtom of the ſaid Merchant-Strangers, they ſhould always come under the Banner and Protection of the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour or Conſuls of <hi>England;</hi> and that never here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they ſhould be vexed or troubled by the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour in this point, the ſaid Embaſſadours of his Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> having deſired that this particular ſhould be written, and inrolled in this new Imperial Capitulation , this preſent Article was accordingly inſerted, and by the Imperial Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority it is commanded, that for ever in time to come, Merchants of the ſaid Princes, in the menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned form, and according to this Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in their hand, ſhall always be under the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Protection of the Embaſſadour and Conſuls of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">XXXIV. There ſhall never be permitted or granted any Imperial Commands contrary to the Tenour and Articles of this Imperial Command or Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">No Imperial Command con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe Articles to be granted.</note> nor in prejudice of this our Peace and Amity, but in ſuch occaſion the cauſe ſhall firſt be certified to the Embaſſadour of <hi>England</hi> reſiding at the Port; to the end, that he may anſwer and object any ſcandalous action, or other pretence, which might infringe the Peace and League.</p>
            <p n="35">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95808:10"/>
               <note place="margin">For enforcing Conſulage.</note>XXXV. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants of all the Merchandize which they ſhall bring or tranſport in their Ships, having paid the Cuſtom, they ſhall alſo pay the Right of Conſulage to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Embaſſadour, or Conſul.</p>
            <p n="36">XXXVI. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, and all under their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhall and may ſafely, throughout our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, trade, buy, ſell, (except only Commodities pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited) all ſorts of Merchandize; likewiſe either by Land or Sea they may go and traffick,<note place="margin">Permiſſion to trade in all parts of the <hi>Turks</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note>or by the way of the River <hi>Tanais</hi> in <hi>Moſcovia,</hi> or by <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> and from thence may bring their Merchandize into our Empire; alſo to and from <hi>Perſia</hi> they may go and trade, and through all that part newly by us conquered, and through thoſe Confines, without the impediment or molestation of any of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; and they ſhall pay the Cuſtom, and other Duties of that Country, and nothing more.</p>
            <p n="37">XXXVII. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, and all under their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Three</hi> per cent. <hi>Cuſtom.</hi>
               </note> ſhall and may ſafely and freely trade and nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate in <hi>Aleppo, Cairo, Scio, Smyrna,</hi> and in all parts of our Dominions; and according to our ancient Cuſtoms of all their Merchandize, they ſhall pay three in the hundred for Cuſtom, and nothing more.</p>
            <p n="38">
               <note place="margin">Veſſels forced by weather.</note>XXXVIII. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships which ſhall come to this our City of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> if by fortune of Seas, or ill weather, they ſhall be forced to <hi>Coffa,</hi> or to ſuch like Port, as long as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will not unlade and ſell their own Merchandize and Goods, no man ſhall enforce them, nor give them any trouble or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95808:11"/>annoyance; but in all places of danger, the Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, or other of our Miniſters ſhall always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships, Men, and Goods, that no damage may come unto them, and with their Money may buy Victuals, and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries; and deſiring alſo with their Money to hire Carts, or Veſſels, which before were not hired by any other, to tranſport their Goods from place to place; no man ſhall do them any hinderance, or trouble whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="39">XXXIX. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, of all the Merchandize which in their Ships ſhall be brought to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Goods not landed, to pay no Cuſtom.</note> or to any other part of our Dominions, which they ſhall not deſire of their own accord to land, or ſell, of ſuch Goods there ſhall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or taken any Cuſtom at arrival at any Port; and having landed their Merchandize, and paid their Cuſtoms, and other Duties, they may quietly and ſafely depart without the moleſtation of any man.</p>
            <p n="40">XL. In regard <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships coming into our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do uſe oftentimes to touch in ſome part of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> and there take in Pilgrims, and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Paſſengers to tranſport them to <hi>Alexandria;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> and arriving at that Port, it ſeemeth that the Cuſtomers and other Officers, do pretend to take Cuſtom of all Goods which are found in their Ships, before the Merchants are willing to land any; by occaſion of which moleſtation they have forborn to tranſport any Pilgrim. And in like manner, their Ships which come to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and carry divers Merchandize, to tranſport part thereof to other places, the Cuſtomers and Farmers would enforce
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95808:11"/>to land, and pretend to take Cuſtom thereof: Wherefore we do command, that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships which with their Merchandize ſhall come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Port of <hi>Conſtantinople, Alexandria, Tripoli</hi> of <hi>Suria, Scanderoon,</hi> or into any Port whatſoever of our Empire; according to uſe, they ſhall pay only Cuſtom of ſuch Goods, which with their own will they ſhall deſign to ſell, and ſuch other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize as they diſcharge not from their Ships willingly our Cuſtomer ſhall not demand, nor take Cuſtom, nor other Duties, but they may tranſport them whitherſoever they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="41">XLI. And if it ſhall happen, that any of the ſaid <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation, or any under their Banner,<note place="margin">Matters of Man-ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Man-ſlaughter, Bloodſhed, or any other like of fence, or that there ſhall happen any cauſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Law or Juſtice, until the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour or Conſul ſhall be preſent to examine the Cauſe, the Judges, nor other Miniſters, ſhall not decide nor give any ſentence, but ſuch controverſie ſhall always be declared in the preſence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour or Conſul, to the end, that no man be judged or condemned contrary to the Law, and the Capitulations.</p>
            <p n="42">XLII. Whereas it is written in the Imperial Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the Goods landed out of any Engliſh Ship, which ſhall come into our Dominions, and pay Cuſtom, ought alſo to pay the duty of Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Embaſſadour or Conſul,<note place="margin">Forreigners Conſulage to be paid.</note> it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that divers <hi>Mahometan</hi> Merchants, <hi>Sciots,</hi> and other Merchants in Peace and Amity with this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Port, and other Merchant-Strangers, do deny and refuſe to pay the right of Conſulage; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95808:12"/>it is commanded, that all the Merchandize which ſhall be laden upon their Ships, and have paid cuſtom, be they goods of whomſoever, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ancient Imperial Capitulations, they ſhall pay the right of Conſulage to the Embaſſadour or Conſul of <hi>England</hi> without any contradiction.</p>
            <p n="43">XLIII. That <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants which trade at <hi>Aleppo,</hi> and thoſe under their Banner,<note place="margin">Silk to pay the Cuſtom, as <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians,</hi> and <hi>French.</hi>
               </note> of all the Silk which they ſhall buy, and lade upon their Ships, ſhall pay the Cuſtom, and other Duties, as the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Venetian</hi> Merchants do pay, and not one Aſper or Farthing more.</p>
            <p n="44">XLIV. As the Embaſſadours of the King of <hi>England,</hi> which ſhall be Reſident in this Imperial Court, are the Repreſentatives and Commiſſioners of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Majeſty, ſo the Interpreters are to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the Commiſſioners of the Embaſſadour: therefore for ſuch matter as the Interpreters ſhall tranſlate or ſpeak in the name,<note place="margin">Interpreters to have licenſe to ſpeak the ſenſe of the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul.</note> or by the order of the Embaſſadour, it being found that that which they have tranſlated to be according to the will and order of the Embaſſadour, or Conſul, they ſhall be always free from any imputation, or puniſhment: And in caſe they ſhall commit any offence,<note place="margin">Drugger-men dying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhall not put any of the ſaid Interpreters in Priſon, nor beat them without knowledge of the Embaſſadour, or Conſul. In caſe any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Interpreters ſhall die, if he be an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man, all his Goods or Faculties ſhall be poſſeſſed by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, or Conſul of <hi>England;</hi> but if he ſhall be a Subject of our Dominion, they ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to his next Heir, and having no Heir, they ſhall be taken into our Exchequer. And as in this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95808:12"/>particular, ſo alſo in all other the above-mentioned Articles and Priviledges granted by our Forefathers of happy memory, it is expreſly commanded and ordained, That all our Slaves ſhall ever obey and obſerve this Imperial Capitulation, and that the Peace and Amity ſhall be reſpected and maintained, without any violation whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="45">
               <note place="margin">No command valid against the Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>XLV. Since which time of our Forefathers of famous memory, and the grant of theſe above-mentioned Capitulations, Articles, and Eſtabliſhment of Peace and Amity, the ſaid King of <hi>England</hi> having in the time of our Grand-father of happy memory, <hi>Sultan Mahomet Han,</hi> ſent one his well deſired Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, a perſon of Quality, to this high Port, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this Peace, Articles and Capitulations: which Ambaſſadour did declare, That oftentimes there were to divers perſons Imperial Commands grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſurreptitiouſly procured contrary to the tenour and Articles of the Imperial Capitulations; which being without our knowledge preſented to our Judges and Governours, and the dates of ſuch Commands being more freſh than thoſe of our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Capitulations, the Judges and Miniſters do put in execution the private Commands prejudicial and contrary to theſe Imperial. To the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that for the time to come, ſuch Commands ſhall not be accepted of any, but that the imperial Capitulations might be always obſerved and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, according to the ſincere meaning; the ſaid Ambaſſador demonſtrating the ſincerity of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and his requeſt herein to our Imperial know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which was moſt acceptable: In conformity thereunto it was expreſly ordered, That all ſuch Commands which already have been, or ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95808:13"/>be granted, which are or ſhall be repugnant to the tenour of this Imperial Capitulation, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſuch Commands ſhall be, when preſented before our Caddees or other Miniſters, ſhould never be accepted or put into execution, but that always the tenour of the Imperial Capitulations ſhall be obſerved: And whoſoever ſhall preſent ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand contrary to the Capitulations,<note place="margin">Such com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</note> they ſhall be taken from him, and in no wiſe be of any force or validity. In which time alſo on the part of our ſaid Grand-father, all the above-written Priviledges, Articles, and Capitulations, were accepted and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and the peace, amity, and good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence anciently contracted was a-new of him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p n="46">XLVI. In the time of the Inauguration of <hi>Sultan Oſman Han</hi> in the Imperial and high Throne, the King of <hi>England</hi> did again ſend a famous and Noble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his Ambaſſadour, with Letters and Preſents which were moſt acceptable. And the ſaid Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour deſiring in the Name of his King and Lord, that the ancient Capitulation, Articles, and Contracts, granted in the days of our Forefathers, ſhould be of him renewed and confirmed, and the ancient peace and amity a-new fortified and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, which his requeſt was to the ſaid <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> moſt acceptable. And the ancient Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Articles, Priviledges, herein written and confirmed, and the long ſince contracted peace and amity by him promiſed and accepted.</p>
            <p n="47">XLVII. After whom in like manner, in the days of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Oſman Han,</hi> the King of <hi>England</hi> having again ſent unto this high Port his Ambaſſadour, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95808:13"/>and Honourable Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> Knight, with his Letters and Preſents, which were moſt acceptable; and proffering in the Name of the King his Lord, all good terms of friendſhip and good correſpondence: And deſiring that the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Capitulations, and all the Articles from his Anceſtors, and from himſelf formerly granted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, might be a-new confirmed, and the peace and league long ſince between both Parties contracted and ratified; and that ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles very neceſſary might be added to the Imperial Capitulations, and divers others already granted might be renewed, amended, and in a better form explained, which his requeſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was very acceptable unto him; and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity thereunto, the ancient Imperial Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all the Articles and other Priviledges in them often confirmed, and the peace, amity, and good correſpondence contracted, in the times of his Anceſtors, Grand-father and Father, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf confirmed, were again by <hi>Sultan Oſman</hi> then ratified, eſtabliſhed, promiſed and accepted, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by him there was expreſs command given, that for the time to come the tenour of his renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Capitulations ſhould be of every one obſerved, and that all men ſhould be careful and reſpectful to the ſaid peace and friendſhip eſtabliſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted on both parts, and that no man ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to violate, or to do any act contrary thereunto, which Ambaſſadour did often declare that the Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, and other of our Miniſters, in many places and Provinces, contrary to the Imperial Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and will of the Imperial Majeſty, have impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laid divers taxes, burdens, and moneys up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and thoſe under their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95808:14"/>Banner, for which cauſe as it is above declared, it being found neceſſary to make additions of ſome new Articles in the ſaid Imperial Capitulation, of which the ſaid Ambaſſadour made declaration in Writing, and preſented the ſame to the Imperial Preſence: The ſaid <hi>Sultan Oſman Han</hi> with his Imperial Hand and Seal did preſently give expreſs order and command, that in the time to come all thoſe Articles and Priviledges which were already in the Imperial Capitulations, and thoſe Articles which now are therein by our order newly added, ſhall be of all our Subjects and Slaves duly obey'd and obſerv'd, according to the ſincere meaning of this our Imperial Capitulations.</p>
            <p n="48">XLVIII. In as much as it is publickly known, That cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Pyrates of <hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Algier,</hi> contrary to our Imperial Capitulations, mind, and will, do take and rob in the Seas the Ships, Merchandiſe, and men, Subjects to his Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> and of other Kings and States in league with this our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Port, to the great dammage and injury of the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation,<note place="margin">Againſt the Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary.</hi>
               </note> We do command and by theſe Presents we do ordain, that ſeveral Imperial Commands be given, for the entire reſtitution of all Goods and Merchandiſe to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation ſo taken away: And that all ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> as have been taken and made Slaves, or impriſoned by the ſaid Pyrates ſhall be immediately ſet free. And after the date of this our Imperial Capitulations, if it ſhall be known that the ſaid Pyrates of <hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Algier</hi> ſhall rob them again, and ſhall uſe and continue their outrages, and will not reſtore their Goods and men, we do command that the ſaid Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates be not received into any Port of our Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95808:14"/>eſpecially into the Scales of <hi>Tunis, Algier, Modon,</hi> or <hi>Coron.</hi> Our Beglerbegs, and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, ſhall not ſuffer them to enter, nor harbour, nor receive them, but the Beglerbegs, Caddees or other Miniſters ſhall perſecute, baniſh and puniſh them.</p>
            <p n="49">XLIX. Being informed that in our Dominions many of our Cuſtomers and other Officers in <hi>Aleppo</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Imperial Capitulations, under colour of taking Cuſtom and Reſt upon Silk of the Engliſh Merchants, have violently taken from the ſaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants a great ſum of Money.<note place="margin">No Reſt to be taken.</note> And whereas in the Imperial Capitulations it is written, that for Silk which the Engliſh ſhall buy in <hi>Aleppo,</hi> they ſhall pay as the French and Venetian Merchants do, and no more; Notwithstanding the ſaid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers, beſides the two and half <hi>per cent.</hi> for Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and Reſt, have taken from that Nation a great ſum of Mony lately under Name of Reſt, wherefore We command that this Buſineſs ſhall be examined, and that the ſaid Mony be reſtored back, and for the time to come, the ancient Cuſtome may be kept; and that this Nation ſhall only pay as the French and Venetian do, and that never be taken one Aſper by name of ſuch Impoſition.</p>
            <p n="50">L Whereas the Engliſh Merchants Reſident in <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata,</hi> ordinarily buy divers Goods and Merchandize before they can Lade or ſend them away upon their Ships, and do pay unto the Cuſtomers the Cuſtome of the ſaid Goods, receiving a Bill,<note place="margin">The Diſcharge of one Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer a ſufficient Acquittance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him that ſucceeds.</note> or Acquittance to have paid the ſame, and after carry the ſame Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize to their own Ware-houſes: In the mean time before they can Load and ſend away the ſaid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95808:15"/>Goods; it happens, that either the Cuſtomer dies, or is removed from his Charge, and the new Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers will not accept of the ſaid Acquittances, but pretend another Cuſtome, troubling and mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of them many ways. Wherefore We do Command, That of all the Merchandize which they ſhall buy, it appearing really that he hath paid once his Cuſtome, the Cuſtomer ſhall accept of the ſaid Acquittances, and ſhall not demand of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant a ſecond Cuſtome.</p>
            <p n="51">LI. It being uſual to buy in <hi>Angora,</hi> Chamblets, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hairs, Silks and other ſorts of Merchandize which they tranſport to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and other places of our Dominions, and pay their Cuſtomes, taking Acquittances for the ſame, and ſo put the Goods into their own Ware-houſes; And after being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to Ship them away, the Cuſtomers do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand again the Cuſtome,<note place="margin">No Cuſtome to be paid twice.</note> Therefore for the time to come, when the ſaid Merchants ſhall deſire to lade ſuch Goods, and it be true that they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paid their Cuſtome of ſuch Merchandize, they ſhall not demand any ſecond or new Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Provided that the laid Merchants do not mingle their Goods, which have not paid Cuſtome with thoſe which have already paid Cuſtome.</p>
            <p n="52">LII. The Engliſh Merchants of all the Merchandize which they ſhall bring into our Dominions, and of the Merchandize which they carry out of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, as Silk, Chamblets and other Goods, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paid the Cuſtome, and not ſold the Goods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; And being afterwards to Ship it away for <hi>Scio, Smyrna,</hi> or any other Scale, and the ſaid Goods there arriving, the Cuſtomers, and Officers,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95808:15"/>ſhall always accept of their Acquittances, which they have in their hands, and ſhall not take other Cuſtome of their Merchandize.</p>
            <p n="53">LIII. The Engliſh Merchants of all the Commodities which they ſhall bring to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or to any other Port of our Dominions, and of all ſuch as they ſhall tranſport,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Meſtaria</hi> to be paid at <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Meſtaragi</hi> of <hi>Galata</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhall take their <hi>Meſtaria</hi> or Brokidge according to the antient Canon and uſance, that is of ſuch Merchandize as of old Cuſtome was wont to pay it, of ſuch they ſhall only take <hi>Meſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> but of ſuch Merchandize as was not antiently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to pay it ſhall not be taken <hi>Meſtaria</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the antient Canon. Farther upon the Engliſh Merchandize, there ſhall not be made or laid any Impoſitions, or other Duties,<note place="margin">No Duties to be raiſed above the accuſtomed uſance.</note> nor from the ſaid Nation ſhall not be taken one Aſper, more, which ſhall be contrary to the antient Canon and accuſtomed uſance.</p>
            <p n="54">LIV. The Engliſh Nation ſhall and may freely come into all the Ports of our Dominions to Negotiate and bring in Cloth, Kerſie, Spice, Tin, Lead, and all other Merchandize, and no man ſhall do them any hinderance or moleſtation. In like manner, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only Goods prohibited, they ſhall and may buy, and export all ſort of Merchandize without the prohibition or moleſtation of any man; and the Cuſtomers, and other Officers, the ſaid Nation having paid their Cuſtome according to this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Capitulation, and the antient uſe, ſhall not demand of them any thing more. In the time of the happy memory of my Uncle Sultan <hi>Murat Han,</hi> the King of <hi>England</hi> ſent his Embaſſador Sir
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95808:16"/>
               <hi>Sackville Crow,</hi> Baronet, with his Preſent and Letter, which was received in good part; and the time of his Embaſſie being expired, Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to reſide at the Port with his Preſent and courteous Letter, the which was in like manner well accepted, And the ſaid Embaſſador having tendered the Imperial Capitulations formerly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that according to the antient Canon they might be renewed; It is hereby again commanded, that all the points, and particular Articles therein be obſerved and maintained.</p>
            <p n="55">
               <note place="margin">No Goods to be forced violently out of the Ships.</note> LV. And becauſe contrary to the fence and tenure of them, the Ships of the Engliſh Merchants before they arrive at the Scale, ſeveral Officers did go upon them, and violently force out of the Ships the Goods of the Merchants, taking away the choice of them without agreeing for the Price, or making any account with the Owners.</p>
            <p n="56">
               <note place="margin">Abuſes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</note>LVI. And farthermore the ſaid Merchants having once payed the Cuſtome for their Goods at the Cuſtome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and being deſirous to tranſport the ſame Goods into another Scale, the Cuſtomers did hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and detain them, until he received another ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Cuſtome for them.</p>
            <p n="57">LVII. And whereas in the Imperial Capitulations it is expreſſed, that in all the differences and Suits with the Engliſh Nation our Magistrates are not to hear nor decide the Cauſe, unleſs their Embaſſador or Conſul be there preſent.<note place="margin">In hearing of Law Suits.</note> Of late our Judges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledg of their Embaſſador have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, impriſoned, and taken Preſents from the Engliſh Nation which is a great wrong done to them.</p>
            <p n="58">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95808:16"/>
               <note place="margin">No Cuſtomes upon Mony</note>LVIII. Alſo whereas in the Imperial Capitulations, it is ordered, that the Cuſtomers ſhall not take any Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for ſuch Gold and Dollars as by the Engliſh Nation ſhall be brought in, or carried out of Our Imperial Dominions, and that the Merchants are to give only three <hi>per cent.</hi> for the Cuſtome of their Goods, and no more; the Cuſtomers not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding do pretend to take Cuſtom for their Chequeens, and Dollars; and to take more Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom then their due for their Raw Silks, which they buy;<note place="margin">Raw Silks.</note> and of the Goods which they land at <hi>Scanderoone</hi> to carry up to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> they demand ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> which unjuſt exactions have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore rectified and redreſſed with an expreſs Hatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheriffe. But being now again informed, that the ſaid Engliſh Merchants, are as before wronged, by reaſon that the Cuſtomers do value and eſtimate the Goods of the Engliſh Merchants more then they are worth; and though the Cuſtomers are to have but three <hi>per cent.</hi> yet by an over valuation of the Goods, they take from them ſix <hi>per cent.</hi> And the Servants of the Cuſtom-houſe, under pretence of ſmall Duties and Expences, wrongfully take great ſums of Mony from them;<note place="margin">A greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans not to be put aboard our Ships then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</note> And a greater number of Waiters being put aboard the Engliſh Ships, then heretofore have been uſed, the charges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are a great expence to the Merchants and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ships that ſuſtain it. To all which, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requeſted for a redreſs, do Command, that when the Cuſtomers do ſet great values upon their Goods, the Merchant offering to them according
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95808:17"/>to the rate of three <hi>per cent. in ſpecie,</hi> of the ſame Goods, the Cuſtomers ſhall not refuſe but accept the ſame. And being deſired by the Engliſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador that the above ſpecified abuſes and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhould be rectified, We do Command, that contrary to the Imperial Capitulations the Engliſh Merchants be neither in the foregoing particulars, nor in any other manner troubled, nor their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges unjuſtly infringed.</p>
            <p>The Embaſſador of the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> Sir <hi>Heneage Finch,</hi> Knight, Earl of <hi>Winchilſea,</hi> Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Maidſton,</hi> Baron <hi>Fitzherbert</hi> of <hi>Eaſtwell,</hi> Lord of the Royal Mannor of <hi>Wye,</hi> and Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and City of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whoſe end may it terminate with bliſs; did arrive with his Preſents, and with all ſincerity, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was accompanied with Letters amply expreſſing the good friendſhip, and correſpondence; and that aboveſaid Embaſſador hath preſented the Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that they might be renewed according to the Canon. And that ſome Articles of great conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration which were before in the Capitulations may be more punctually obſerved, the ſaid Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador did deſine, that they, might be again renewed, and more plainly expreſſed in the Imperial Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. His requeſt was graciouſly accepted; one of which Points is this.</p>
            <p n="59">LIX. That the Gallies, and other Veſſels of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Fleet departing the Dominions of the Grand
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95808:17"/>Signor, and meeting on the Sea with the Ships of <hi>England,</hi> they ſhall in no wiſe give them moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor detain them in their Voyage, nor take from them any thing whatſoever, but ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to ſhew to one another good friendſhip, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing the leaſt damage. And it being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the Imperial Capitulations,<note place="margin">The Pyrates of <hi>Barbary</hi> not to ſearch our Ships for Strangers Goods.</note> Beyes and Captains, who Sail upon the Seas, and thoſe of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier, Tunis,</hi> and <hi>Tripoli,</hi> meeting Engliſh Ships which Sail from one Port to another, ought not to take from them any Mony or goods, upon pretence that their Ships tranſport Enemies Goods, and thereupon ſearch them, and with this colour mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, and detain them from proſecution of their Voyage, ſo that only at the mouth of the Caſtles, and in the Ports where the Searchers belonging to the Cuſtoms uſually come aboard, their Goods ſhall be examined, but on the Sea, they ſhall be lyable to no farther ſearch or inquiſition.</p>
            <p n="60">LX. And contrary to the Articles of the Imperial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulations, the Goods of the Engliſh Nation ought to receive no moleſtation having once paid the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,<note place="margin">Cuſtoms being paid, the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer not to deny the Teſchere.</note> nor ſhall the Cuſtomers deny to give the Teſchere, or Certificate, that the Cuſtom is paid for; upon complaint hereof, We ſtrictly Command that the aforeſaid Cuſtomers do not defer immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon demand to give the Teſchere or Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</p>
            <p n="61">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95808:18"/>
               <note place="margin">A ſecond Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom not to be demanded.</note>LXI. And the Cuſtome being once paid of any ſort of Merchandize not ſold in that Port, which is to be tranſported to another Scale, entire credit ſhall be given to the Teſchere, and a ſecond Cuſtom ſhall not be ſo much as farther pretended.</p>
            <p n="62">LXII. In <hi>Aleppo, Cairo,</hi> and other parts of the Imperial Dominions, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants and their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may freely and frankly trade,<note place="margin">All Goods in Engliſh Ships, as well as thoſe of the growth and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> not to pay above three <hi>per cent.</hi> Cuſtom.</note> and for all their Goods and Merchandize pay only three <hi>per Cent.</hi> according to the former Cuſtom and the Imperial Capitulations, whether the Goods be brought by Sea or by Land. And though the Cuſtomers and Farmers, upon the arrival of the Goods at the Scale, to give moleſtation and trouble to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, pretend that the Goods of the growth and manufacture of <hi>England</hi> ought only to pay three <hi>per Cent.</hi> but Goods brought from <hi>Venice</hi> and other places are obliged to pay more, and with this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and pretence occaſion ſuits, and troubles to the Engliſh; wherefore in this point let the Imperial Capitulations be obſerved as in former times, and Our Officers ought in no wiſe to permit the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereunto.</p>
            <p n="63">
               <note place="margin">Without Pledge or Suretyſhip one Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>LXIII. An Engliſhman becoming indebted, or having made himſelf Pledge for another, who is either fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95808:18"/>or run away; the Debt ought to be demanded of the Debtor; And if the Creditor have no Hoget that ſuch an one according to the Law hath made himſelf Pledge and ſecurity, the Debt ſhall not be demanded of the other, which Article is already declared in the Capitulations.</p>
            <p n="64">
               <note place="margin">Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, cannot be enforced.</note>LXIV. Whereas ſometimes an Engliſhman living in a Country, to free himſelf from a Debt draws a Bill of Exchange upon another Engliſhman who hath no Effects of his in his hands; and the perſon to whom the Mony is payable being a man of Power, and Authority, brings his Bill, and contrary to the Law, and the Capitulations, demands and forces payment of the Bill. In which caſe the Merchant accepting the Bill, ſhall be obliged to ſatisfie it, but not accepting of it, he ſhall be lyable to no farther trouble.</p>
            <p n="65">
               <note place="margin">Drugermen free of all <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> and the <hi>Caſſam.</hi>
               </note>LXV. And the Interpreters of the Embaſſador of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being free by the Articles, declared in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Capitulations, of all <hi>Angaria,</hi> or Taxes; by vertue alſo of this preſent Article, when any of the ſaid Interpreters die, their Goods, or Eſtate ſhall not be ſubject to the Cuſtom, but ſhall be devided amongſt the Creditors, and Heirs.</p>
            <p n="66">LXVI. And the King of <hi>England</hi> being a true Friend
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95808:19"/>to this Our happy Port,<note place="margin">Ten of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants free of Harach.</note> To his Embaſſador who reſides here ten Servants, of what Nation ſoever, ſhall be allowed free from Harach or Taxes, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation of any man.</p>
            <p n="67">LXVII. An Engliſhman turning Mahometan, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Goods, or Eſtate in his hands belonging to his Engliſh Principals,<note place="margin">The Eſtate of Principals the hand of a Renegado to be delivered to the Embaſſador or Conſul.</note> thoſe goods or Eſtate ſhall be delivered into the hands of the Embaſſador, or Conſul, that they may convey, and make them good to the true Owners.</p>
            <p>The late Embaſſadour of the King of <hi>England</hi> who reſided in our high Port being dead, Sir <hi>John Finch,</hi> Knight, a prudent man, and one of the Council of Foreign Trade, is appointed to ſucceed him in the Charge of the Embaſſy: And notice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given to our Noble Preſence, that the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour was arrived with the Royal Letters and the uſual Preſents, they were acceptable to us. And the aforeſaid Embaſſador having made known to us, that in the Capitulations already granted, there were ſeveral expreſſions ſo full of ambiguity, that they needed further explication; and to this end having requeſted of us, in the behalf of the King his Maſter, that the Capitulations might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and that ſuch Explications and additional Articles as were neceſſary might be added to them; the Requeſt of the ſaid Ambaſſador being made known to us, We have conſented to it: And We do command, and be it commanded, that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95808:19"/>deſired be added to the former Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; of which one is,</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>Niſani Sheriff</hi> (that is) the Imperial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, upon which was put the <hi>Hatterſheriff</hi> (that is) the Hand of the Emperour <hi>Sultan Ibrahim Han</hi> (whoſe Soul reſt in glory) in the year 1053. which Command declares, that anciently the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships that came to <hi>Scanderoon,</hi> did pay for every Cloth of <hi>London</hi> for the Cuſtom of <hi>Scanderoon</hi> forty <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's;</hi> and for a piece of Kerſey ſix <hi>Para's;</hi> and for every Bundle of Cony-Skins ſix <hi>Para's;</hi> and for Tin and Lead, for every Quintal of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> or <hi>Cantaro</hi> fifty ſeven <hi>Para's</hi> and a half for Cuſtom; which Goods afterwards arriving in <hi>Aleppo</hi> did pay for the Cuſtom of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> for every Cloth of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> eight <hi>Para's,</hi> for a Piece of Kerſey eight <hi>Para's</hi> and one ſixth, for every Bundle of Cony-Skins eight <hi>Para's</hi> and one ſixth, for Tin and Lead for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Battman of <hi>Aleppo</hi> one <hi>Para</hi> for Cuſtom. And the ſaid Nation buying Goods &amp; tranſporting them, for what they bought in <hi>Aleppo</hi> and exported, did pay for raw Cloth of Linen or Chilis, for Cordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans, for <hi>Hora ſani Hindi,</hi> for every Bale of each two Dollars and a half; and for every Bale of Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Yarn a Dollar and a quarter, and for a Bale of Gauls a quarter of a Dollar, and for every Bale of Silk ten <hi>Oſmani</hi> (of which fourteen makes a Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) for Rhubarb, and ſuch like Drugs, three Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars for every hundred, according to the eſtimate of the chief in that Art. The ſaid Goods carried to <hi>Scanderoon,</hi> and there loaden upon their Ships,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95808:20"/>did pay for Raw Linen-cloth, or Chilis, for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovans, each a Dollar and a half the Bale for the Cuſtom of <hi>Scanderoon;</hi> for <hi>Hora ſani Hindi</hi> and Cotton Yarn, three quarters of a Dollar the Bale, for a Bale of Gauls one quarter of a Dollar, for Rhubarb and like Drugs, according to the eſteem of Druggiſts, three quartes of a Dollar the Bale; and nothing more is to be, or ought to be paid, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenour of this ſublime Command: And if the <hi>Teſterdar</hi> ſhall give any Command con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, let it not be obeyed, but be eſteemed invalid: But let every thing be obſerved confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to this Imperial Command and Imperial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulations.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants for all Goods exported or imported paid three <hi>per cent.</hi> only, and never ought to pay an Aſper more, it being ſo ſpecified in the Imperial Capitulations: But there having in the Scales of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Galata</hi> aroſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traſts and differences with the Cuſtomers concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Londra's,</hi> or Cloth brought from <hi>London,</hi> and other ſorts of Cloth of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufacture, they ſhall pay according to the accuſtomed and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canon, and as they have always hitherto paid, that is to ſay of full Aſpers, or ſhort money, of which Aſpers eighty make a piece of eight, and ſeventy a <hi>Lion</hi> Dollar, Aſpers one hundred forty and four, for every piece of Cloth of <hi>Engliſh</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, whether ſine or courſe, and of whatſoever price, and the Cuſtomer ſhall not demand more, nor ought not to take more: But the Cloth that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95808:20"/>comes from <hi>Holland,</hi> and other Countries, <hi>viz. Londrini,</hi> Says and Scarlets, and other ſorts of Cloth not <hi>Engliſh</hi> fabrick, ſhall pay for the future that which hitherto has been the accuſtomed Duty. And at the Scale of <hi>Smyrna</hi> ſhall be paid according to the ancient Cuſtom and Uſe of full Aſpers, or ſhort Money, of which Aſpers eighty make a piece of eight, and ſeventy a <hi>Lion</hi> Dollar; Aſpers one hundred and twenty for every piece of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth, whether fine or courſe, whether <hi>Londra</hi> or not, provided that it be of the fabrick of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And the Cuſtomer ſhall not demand, nor ought not to take, one Aſper more, and let no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation be made upon the Cuſtom of the ſaid Cloths.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Capitulations being known, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> having a Controverſie, the import of which is above four thouſand Aſpers, that the Cauſe ſhall be brought to the <hi>Porta,</hi> and tryed no where elſe; if at any time the Caddi or Miniſters of any place would detain any Merchant, or hinder any <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man that comes upon a Ship, from proſecuting their Voyage by reaſon of any Money impoſed upon them, or pretended from them, if the Conſul of the place will be Security to anſwer the Pretenſions made before the <hi>Porta,</hi> ſuch Perſons ſhall be free and at liberty to proſecute their Voyage; and they that pretend any thing of them, let them come to the <hi>Divan</hi> for to be judged, and let the Embaſſadour defend them from theſe that come to demand; but if the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul will not, be Security, then let the Judge of the place give Sentence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:95808:21"/>In <hi>Conſtantinople, Scanderone, Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and all other Ports and Scales of my Empire, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships ſhall arrive, they ſhall pay three hundred Aſpers for Anchorage or Port Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and there ſhall not, nor ought not to be taken or paid one Aſper more.</p>
            <p n="5">V. An <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man coming with Effects and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Muſſulman, the Embaſſadour or Conſul knowing that ſuch Effects do belong to other <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Merchants, let all the Money and other Effects be taken out of the hand of ſuch a Muſſulman, and conſigned to the Embaſſadour; to the end that he may tranſmit them to whom they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, that by this means no Goods of other men may remain in the hands of ſuch a Muſſulman; and let not this be hindred by the means of any <hi>Caddi,</hi> or other Judges or Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Any of the aforeſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation buying <hi>Chambelets, Mochairs,</hi> or <hi>Grogran-yarne</hi> in <hi>Angora,</hi> or <hi>Begbazar,</hi> if they will export the ſaid Goods from thoſe places, after having paid three <hi>per cent.</hi> for the Cuſtom of ſuch Goods they export, let them not be moleſted for <hi>Skraz Batch,</hi> that is, for Paſſage or Exportation; and there neither ſhall nor
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95808:21"/>ought to be taken upon the account of any ſuch Dem and one Aſper.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant being to receive from his Debtor any ſum of Money, if the ſaid Debt be recovered by the means and help of an Aſſiſtant or <hi>Chiaus,</hi> he that recovers the Debt ſhall pay no more than what is paid to other <hi>Caddi</hi>'s, which is two Aſpers only, and not one Aſper more.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. There paſſing good correſpondence between Us and the King of <hi>England;</hi> out of regard of this good Friendſhip, We do grant that two Ships lading of Figs, Raiſins or Currants may be yearly Exported for the uſe of his Majeſty's Kitchin, if there be not a dearth and ſcarcity of ſuch Fruit in the Country; which we allow to be bought with their Money that Export them at the Scale of <hi>Smyrna, Salonica,</hi> or any other Scale or Port of our Empire, paying three <hi>per Cent.</hi> Cuſtom, which being paid no perſon ſhall give to them that lade them any moleſtation or hindrance.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. It being repreſented to Us, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been accuſtomed hitherto to pay no Cuſtom nor <hi>Mezan</hi> for any Silk they bought in <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:95808:22"/>(that of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> excepted) <hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for the Silk of <hi>Giorgia, Perſia,</hi> or <hi>Armenia;</hi> if really there is any ſuch Uſe and Cuſtom, and the thing is not of prejudice to the Empire, let there in <hi>Smyrna</hi> for the future be demanded neither Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom nor Mezan for the ſaid Silk, but. to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Merchants let all kindneſs be uſed and ſhown. And the Embaſſador having made inſtance to Us that the foregoing Articles might be put into the Capitulations, his Request is granted, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the former Imperial Sign and Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, let now in conformity of what was paſſed, and of my Imperial Command, be renewed and granted this preſent Imperial Capitulation: which We command ſo long as <hi>Charles</hi> the Second King of <hi>England</hi> (whoſe end may it terminate in hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs) maintains good Friendſhip and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with Us, according to what has been maintained with our Ancestors, and to which We on our part are not wanting, with all tenderneſs entertaining this Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>And we do ſwear and promiſe by him that has Created the Heaven and the Earth, and all the Creatures; by the Creator the one God We do promiſe, that nothing ſhall be done contrary to this Imperial Capitulation; and accordingly every one is to obey our Imperial Sign.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given in the middle of the Moon</hi> Gemaziel Akir 1086. <hi>in the Imperial City of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drianople, <hi>being in</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the Month of</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:95808:22"/>
The Grand Signor writes above with his own hand as follows.
<signed>Let every thing be obſerved in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to our IMPERIAL COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAND, and contrary to it let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
